# Cailin Nivene Pillay

### **Data Analyst Manager**

19 West Street, Cravenby, Elsies River, 7490, Western Cape, Cape Town, South Africa

+27 82 559 1967

Date of birth: 1999/05/19

Driving License: Code B

**SOCIAL PROFILES** 

\* Email: Cailin Pillay

\* LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/cailin-pillay-122092152/

\* My Portfolio: https://cailinp05.github.io/

\* Github: <a href="https://github.com/Cailinp05">https://github.com/Cailinp05</a>

### **Summary**

#### **LANGUAGES**

\*\*\*\* English

\*\*\* Afrikaans

\*\* A AFRIKAANS

\*\* A AFRIKAANS

\*\* A AFRIKAANS

#### **SKILLS**

★★★★ Data Analysis

★★★★ R

★★★★ SQL

★★★★ PowerBI

★★★★ Excel

★★★★ Data Visualization

★★★★ HTML

★★★★ Python

I am a Data Analyst Manager with a strong Biodiversity and Conservation Biology background. I have experience working as a Data Analyst at APS Holdings, where I collect and clean data to create visualizations in Navicat MYSQL, Excel, and PowerBI. I also have experience as a Benthic Ecologist Data Science Intern at the University of the Western Cape, where I developed and executed algorithms and predictive models to analyze large datasets. In addition, I have held various positions at Ruhenssoutafrica/Neutratech, including Regional Branch Manager, Sales Manager, Team Leader, and Personal Assistant. I have a BSc in Biodiversity and Conservation Biology and a Data Analytics Professional Certificate from Google. With my strong skills in SQL, Tableau, R, PowerBI, Github, Python, and data analysis, I am confident in transforming complex data into actionable insights. My future goals include leading a data analytical team and building a successful company.

### Experience

#### **Data Analyst at APS Holdings, Cape Town**

JANUARY 2024 - Present, Milnerton

As a Data Analyst Manager at APS Holdings, I am responsible for analyzing and interpreting complex data sets to provide valuable insights and support decision-making processes. I utilize my skills in mySQL, excel, PowerBI and data analysis to extract and manipulate data, conduct statistical analyses, and create visualizations. Additionally, I collaborate with cross-functional teams to identify trends, patterns, and opportunities for improvement. Through my work, I contribute to enhancing business performance and driving data-driven strategies.

Analyze and interpret complex data sets to provide valuable insights for decision-making processes.

Utilize SQL, Excel, and PowerBI to extract and manipulate data. Conduct statistical analyses to identify trends, patterns, and opportunities for improvement.

Optimized database performance by designing efficient data models and indexing

Analyzed and visualized large datasets to uncover key insights, resulting in a R 6000000 increase in revenue for the company

Conducted ad-hoc analyses to answer business questions and provide insights to stakeholders, resulting in improved operational efficiency and cost savings

Created a dashboard that visually represented key business metrics in real-time, allowing for quick and informed decision-making by management.

#### Google/Data Analytics Professional Certificate

JULY 2023 - SEPTEMBER 2023, Online

Completed extensive six-month job-read Google Career Certificate training. Demonstrated hands-on experience with data cleaning, data visualization, project management, interpreting and communicating data analytics findings. Confidence in transforming complex data into actionable and clear insights. Fluency in computer programming languages and a solid understanding of databases.

### KPMG AU/Data Analytics Consulting Virtual Internship Certificate

SEPTEMBER 2023 - NOVEMBER 2023, Online (Australia)

From September 2023 to November 2023, I completed practical tasks in Data Quality Assessment, Data Insights, Data Insights, and Presentation.

### Bootcamp with Alex the Analyst Data Analytics Professional Certificate

NOVEMBER 2023, Online

I have completed the Data Analytics Bootcamp by Alex Freberg. Along with building exciting real-time projects, this bootcamp covered each

topic comprehensively. I've mastered Advanced SQL, Python, Power BI, Tableau, and Advanced Excel through this course.

### Ruhenssoutafrica /Regional Branch Manager, Sales Manager, Team Leader, and Personal Assistant

15 MARCH 2019 - 05 AUGUST 2023, Hybrid/Tygervalley/Table View

Promoted with 7 positions at the same company, increasing sales, building and managing a team, personal assistant, admin assistant, branch and sales manager, etc. I used Data Analytics and Excel to monitor sales activities, maintenance bookings, debit orders, and general ledgers to ensure customer satisfaction services and good quality services. Created a positive atmosphere for clientele, responding to customer inquiries and complaints. Monitored, directed and prioritized all company front end and back end activities in a fast-paced environment. Conducting demonstrations and created quotes, invoicing, debit orders, maintenance booking, new client monitoring, creating, and managing social media platforms. Aiding in launching a successful business by ensuring quality customer service and personal assistant working closely with the CEO of the company.

### University of the Western Cape / Benthic Ecologist Data Science Internship

9 AUGUST 2021 - 9 DECEMBER 2022, Hybrid/Belville

Writing my own code in R programming language for scientific purposes, this aided in my entire honours project being done in R/R markdown, and Github (https://github.com/Cailinp05). Working closely with a Professor at the University of the Western Cape to develop, validate, and execute basic algorithms, predictive models to collect, merge, analyze, extract, and interpret large datasets. Acquire, combine and transform data from various sources into interpretable datasets. Using data to investigate scientific problems, detect patterns and extrapolate insights into a scientific paper. Developing data structures, organizing, collecting, standardizing data, performing data preparation in order to reduce and shape data. Clean and validate data and assure its integrity, accuracy, completeness and uniformity. Test data mining models to select the most appropriate one for use on the project. Adhere to stringent quality assurance and documentation standards using version control and code repositories. Cross-validate models to ensure their generalizability. Assess the effectiveness of data sources and data-gathering techniques to improve data collection methods, and data management and governance in terms of data protection, compliance, retention, archiving guidelines, data standards etc. Prepare analytical findings, results and reports using data visualization techniques. Effectively structure and plan projects, timelines, and deliverables, working with the Professor on technical trade-offs. Conduct research from which to develop prototypes and proof of concepts, specifically LiDAR technology. Share insights and knowledge across teams to inform collaborative efforts via PowerPoint presentations to the entire department and conferences. Stay updated on the latest research and developments in Data Science and adjacent fields to ensure the latest technology, techniques and methods are always applied. All while remaining high in self-motivation and drive to meet and exceed goals and expectations.

#### **Education**

## University of the Western Cape / BSC Biodiversity and Conservation Biology Honours

17 FEBRUARY 2022 - 21 DECEMBER 2023, Belville

Completed Honours degree and honours project based in R programming language as mentioned above linked with experience from the Benthic Ecologist Data Science Internship. This year also includes modules such as marine biology, herpetology, quantitative ecology in R, and biostatistic in R.

## University of the Western Cape / BSC Biodiversity and Conservation Biology

17 FEBRUARY 2017 - 20 MAY 2021, Belville

Completed undergraduate degree while working full time at promotional companies and retail stores. The degree included mathematics, statistics, chemistry, earth science, estuarine ecology, scientific article writing and ethics, life science, and environmental and water science.

### **Awards and Courses**

- Top sales Agent and Branch Manager at Ruhensouthafrica/Neutratech.
- Data Science Course at Digital Regenesys. PRACE Supercomputing MOOC and CHPC Practical HPC course through Future Learn CHPC Winter School 2021.
- The Data Science Course 2022: Complete Data Science Bootcamp on Udemy.
- KPMG AU/Data Analytics Consulting Virtual Internship Certificate.
- Bootcamp with Alex the Analyst Data Analytics Professional Certificate.
- Google/Data Analytics Professional Certificate.
- Professional Snake Handling and First Aid Course at African Snakebite Institute.
- Professional Scorpion Handling and First Aid Course at African Snakebite Institute.
- CPR/AED certified 2022 (Adults and babies).
- Young Biologist Course at the Two Oceans Aquarium.
- Marine and Oceanography Course at the Two Oceans Aquarium.
- Grades 1 7 Silver Flute and Music Theory Grade 1 4 at Trinity College London.
- Oualified Freediver.